Speaker: Law and order, 1
Prison sentences
Ideally, the fear of punishment
should discourage people from committing a crime in the first place.
However, studies show that, while short to medium prison sentences may be a deterrent,
longer sentences have only a limited effect. In deciding the sentence,
the court will take into consideration things like the seriousness of the offence,
whether the defendant pleads guilty or not guilty,
and whether their criminal record shows that they are a serial offender.
The judge will also consider any mitigating circumstances, e.g. diminished responsibility,
i.e. the person’s mental state means that they are not fully responsible for a crime.
Sentences can be non- custodial: a fine is paid,
or community service, such as unpaid work, is carried out.
A custodial sentence is handed down for more serious crimes,
and for the most serious offences such as murder, it’s a life sentence.